<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"> <title>Misc ramblings, by rlazo</title> <link href="http://rlazo.github.io/blog"/> <link type="application/atom+xml" rel="self" href="http://rlazo.github.io/blog/atom.xml"/> <updated>Fri, 28 Nov 2014 01:00:20 -0200</updated> <author> <name>Rodrigo Lazo</name> </author> <entry> <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://rlazo.github.io/blog/posts/Performance-evaluation.html"/> <title>Performance evaluation</title> <published>2014-11-27 22:40:00</published> <updated>2014-11-27 22:40:00</updated> <author> <name>Rodrigo Lazo</name> <uri>http://rlazo.github.io/blog</uri> </author> <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I read a couple of days ago a blog post by
&lt;a href=&quot;https://homes.cs.washington.edu/~bornholt&quot; &gt;James Bornholt&lt;/a&gt;, PhD
Candidate @ UW, about
&lt;a href=&quot;https://homes.cs.washington.edu/~bornholt/post/performance-evaluation.html&quot; &gt;Performance evaluation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His focus seems to be on programming languages and compilers, and the
article deals mainly with how &lt;em&gt;details&lt;/em&gt; as minor as linking order can
affect the performance of an application. He even makes the point that
a compiler generating two binaries of the same code &lt;em&gt;does not&lt;/em&gt; result
in equally performing binaries (with up to 7% variation). This extreme
case was caused by a bug in the compiler, which can make us think that
it isn&#039;t a good example for the point he&#039;s trying to make. Actually,
in this case, any benchmark of binaries produced by that compiler, in
the time the bug was present (10 years!), in which the difference is
around 7%, cannot be considered valid. Mind blowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, he mentions how benchmarking suites, even if we know that they
aren&#039;t very good to measure real-world performance, are being missued
to generate almost worthless measurements. In short, a benchmark suite
runs several cases to try to simulate a variety of scenarios that can
occur in the real world. But some people are ignoring some of the test
of the suites, and then assuming that the result of the benchmark is
meaningful, which is not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole article is not so long and definitely worth reading.&lt;/p&gt;
</content> </entry><entry> <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://rlazo.github.io/blog/posts/Understanding-autoloads.html"/> <title>Understanding autoloads</title> <published>2014-11-20 10:40:00</published> <updated>2014-11-20 10:40:00</updated> <author> <name>Rodrigo Lazo</name> <uri>http://rlazo.github.io/blog</uri> </author> <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Eventhough I&#039;ve been working and twicking emacs for over a decade, I
somehow managed to avoid using autoloads in my code until now. Which,
in the bright side, was great because
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lunaryorn.com/&quot; &gt;Sebastian Wiesner&lt;/a&gt; recently posted an
awesome, and very detailed, guide to
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lunaryorn.com/2014/07/02/autoloads-in-emacs-lisp.html&quot; &gt;Autoloads in Emacs Lisp&lt;/a&gt;.
Learning about emacs is getting easier and easier :)&lt;/p&gt;
</content> </entry><entry> <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://rlazo.github.io/blog/posts/Learning-some-R.html"/> <title>Learning some R</title> <published>2014-11-16 21:40:10</published> <updated>2014-11-16 21:40:10</updated> <author> <name>Rodrigo Lazo</name> <uri>http://rlazo.github.io/blog</uri> </author> <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This weekend I&#039;ve been helping my brother with an issue with an R
script he needs for his masters. And &lt;strong&gt;my God&lt;/strong&gt;, that was one ugly
script. It was pretty obvious that the original author, not my
brother, didn&#039;t know very well how to write good scripts, neither was
interested in learning. What a big hairy mess of R code. It was my first
time working with R and, while I didn&#039;t find it as ugly as I
originally though, I hope that I don&#039;t have to mess with it
too often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of you that don&#039;t know, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.r-project.org/&quot; &gt;R&lt;/a&gt; is a
programming language mostly used for statistics. Actually, from what
I&#039;ve read, it&#039;s mostly referred to as a &lt;em&gt;software environment&lt;/em&gt;. What&#039;s
the difference? Well, it has a
&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Read%E2%80%93eval%E2%80%93print_loop&quot; &gt;REPL&lt;/a&gt;
and it&#039;s usually used inside a sort of IDE like
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rstudio.com/&quot; &gt;RStudio&lt;/a&gt;. But, unlike Python or Lisp, that
you usally use the REPL for testing and development, but you write
your &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; code in a file, in R most of the beginners usually work
only in the REPL, and the file is more like a history of ran commands
than a cohesive script. And, because there is a lot of people that
uses R but are not very interested in programming per-se, the scripts
are extremely brittle and only work under very specific assumptions,
there are no comments, a lot of lines are just debugging commands that
only make sense in the repl, dead variables left from previous
experiments, and a long etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting the original code to a readable state took us two days, and
it&#039;s not done yet. While not knowing R did slow us down somewhat
considerably, the worst part was trying to understand what the code
was trying to do. On the upside, this was a great opportunity to
explain to my brother about code readability, de-compsition, comments,
top-down and bottom-up designs, etc. After all the pain of having to
work through a great example of what happens if you don&#039;t use those
concepts, he was an eager and learner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This remind me of some wise words a teacher told me once: &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;you are
only going to learn the true value of these good practices the day you
have to painfully work on a code that doesn&#039;t follow them&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amen.&lt;/p&gt;
</content> </entry><entry> <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://rlazo.github.io/blog/posts/Blogging-again-powered-by-coleslaw.html"/> <title>Blogging again, powered by coleslaw</title> <published>2014-11-16 20:40:10</published> <updated>2014-11-16 20:40:10</updated> <author> <name>Rodrigo Lazo</name> <uri>http://rlazo.github.io/blog</uri> </author> <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hardly anyone would know that but I used to have another blog @
rlazo.org, but I no longer have the domain or the blog for that
matter. I starting anew with this blog using a static blog engine
written in Common Lisp called
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/redline6561/coleslaw&quot; &gt;coleslaw&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot; &gt;github pages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why using github pages? It&#039;s easy, and has far less moving parts than
any other option I can think off. I don&#039;t have a server to manage, and
the publish blog is static html. The only way of changing the contents
of the blog is changing them in the repo. So, it&#039;s more secure than
more dynamic options, like wordpress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why coleslaw? Well, I&#039;m a fanboy of Common Lisp, and the code isn&#039;t
complicated or long, so making changes, if needed, &lt;em&gt;should be easy
(TM)&lt;/em&gt;. The other two pieces of software that I use the most,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/&quot; &gt;my editor&lt;/a&gt; and my
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/stumpwm/stumpwm&quot; &gt;window manager&lt;/a&gt;, are also written
in lisp. You can see a trend here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully I&#039;ll be posting more, and some of the contents may even be
in spanish. Wish me luck.&lt;/p&gt;
</content> </entry> </feed>